IN SURGERY, SONG HA-YOUNG
수술중인 송하영
Luckily, he's out of the woods for now.
운 좋게도 그는 지금은 숲 밖에 있습니다.
Once we wrap up, we'll move him to the ICU
마무리되면 중환자실로 옮기겠습니다
and monitor his recovery.
그의 회복을 모니터링하십시오.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
Thank you. Good work.
감사합니다. 잘 했어.
I should've taken better care of him.
내가 그를 더 잘 보살펴줬어야 했는데.
It's all right.
괜찮아요.
I know he's going to wake up soon.
나는 그가 곧 깨어날 것이라는 것을 알고 있습니다.
He will.
그는 할 것이다.
Was I six years old then?
그때 제가 6살이었나요?
I went to an amusement park with my mother on Children's Day.
어린이날에 엄마랑 놀이공원에 갔어요 .
That was the first time I saw a dead body.
그때 처음으로 시체를 봤습니다.
You were pretty young.
당신은 꽤 어렸습니다.
The body was in the water.
시체는 물속에 있었습니다.
When I saw her face,
그녀의 얼굴을 봤을 때
she didn't scare me.
그녀는 나를 겁주지 않았습니다.
She just looked very lonely.
그녀는 매우 외로워 보였습니다.
"She must have been terrified."
"그녀는 겁에 질렸나 봐요."
"She must've been lonely and in pain."
"그녀는 분명 외롭고 고통스러웠을 것입니다."
That's what crossed my mind.
그것이 내 마음속에 떠올랐습니다.
So I wanted to reach out to hold her hand.
그래서 나는 그녀의 손을 잡고 싶었습니다.
But I couldn't do that back then.
하지만 그때는 그렇게 할 수 없었어요.
Just like what you've been doing,
당신이 해왔던 것과 마찬가지로,
you probably did something to help the woman back then.
아마 당신은 그 당시 그 여자를 돕기 위해 뭔가를 했을 겁니다.
The Southwest Case serial killer, Nam Ki-Tae,
사우스웨스트 사건 연쇄살인범 남기태
said he'd kill again if he were released,
풀려나면 또 살인하겠다고 하더군요
which shocked the public.
대중을 놀라게 했습니다.
We should hang men like him in the middle of Gwanghwamun
저런놈을 광화문 한복판에 매달아야지
and stone them to death.
그리고 그들을 돌로 쳐 죽입니다.
Why do people want to keep him alive? I really don't get it.
사람들은 왜 그를 살려두려고 할까요? 정말 이해가 안 돼요.
What he did was inhumane. He doesn't deserve human rights.
그가 한 일은 비인간적이었습니다. 그 사람은 인권을 누릴 자격이 없어요.
Sir, I'm sorry, but could you turn that off please?
선생님, 죄송 하지만 그 기능을 꺼주시겠어요?
It's giving me a headache.
머리가 아프네요.
Right. Sure.
오른쪽. 확신하는.
This news isn't that pleasant to listen to.
이 소식은 듣기에 그다지 유쾌하지 않습니다 .
TOJUNG-DONG, ANYANG, GYEONGGI PROVINCE
경기도 안양시 토중동
What?
무엇?
I'm in Tojung-dong right now.
저는 지금 토중동에 있어요.
I need to check out a missing person case.
실종자 사건을 확인해야 해요.
I'll be there later.
나중에 갈게요.
HERO KARAOKE BAR
히어로 가라오케 바
-Excuse me. -We're not open yet.
-실례합니다. -아직 문을 열지 않았습니다.
I see.
알겠어요.
-I'm from the police. -Hello.
-저는 경찰 출신이에요. -안녕하세요.
You're my lady lady
당신은 나의 레이디 레이디
I can't live without you
당신 없이는 살 수 없어요
The only thing I need in my life is you
내 인생에 필요한 유일한 것은 당신입니다
Are you having fun?
당신은 재미?
I got bored of waiting.
기다리는 것이 지루해졌습니다.
Brief me.
나에게 편지를 보내세요.
I told you over the phone.
제가 전화로 말씀드렸어요.
So she left after singing here.
그래서 그녀는 여기서 노래를 부르고 떠났다.
-And then she can't be reached. -Right.
-그러면 연락이 안 돼요. -오른쪽.
She left alone without a customer?
손님도 없이 혼자 떠났다고?
Right.
오른쪽.
-That's it? -Right.
- 그게 다야? -오른쪽.
A woman in her forties was having fun with her customer here.
이곳에서는 40대 여성이 손님과 즐거운 시간을 보내고 있었습니다.
And she left before the customer,
그리고 그녀는 고객보다 먼저 떠났고,
and she can't be reached ever since.
그 이후로는 그녀에게 연락할 수 없습니다.
Is that really it?
그게 정말인가요?
Right.
오른쪽.
Come on.
어서 해봐요.
Chief Park.
박 과장.
I came all the way here.
나는 여기까지 왔습니다.
You should have gotten a lead.
당신은 단서를 얻었어야 했어요.
I didn't ask you to come here.
나는 당신에게 여기로 오라고 요청하지 않았습니다.
-You came here on your own. -Damn you.
-당신은 혼자 여기에 왔습니다. -젠장.
You want me to report this
이거 신고하라고 하네
as criminal intelligence?
범죄정보로?
You do it. I'm out.
당신은 그것을 할. 나는 나갔다.
Another woman from a different karaoke bar went missing in February.
지난 2월에는 다른 노래방의 또 다른 여성이 실종됐다.
What?
무엇?
MISSING PERSON
실종자
Two cases?
두 가지 경우?
Yes.
예.
In February, a female worker
2월에는 여직원이
at a karaoke bar in Suwon went missing.
수원의 한 노래방에서 실종됐다.
-But that case hasn't been filed yet. -Why not?
-그런데 그 사건은 아직 접수되지 않았는데요. -왜 안 돼?
A lot of these workers often go AWOL and move to another karaoke bar.
이들 근로자 중 다수는 종종 무단이탈하여 다른 노래방으로 이동합니다.
I guess that's why.
그래서 그런 것 같아요.
But how did you come across this case? This wasn't filed.
그런데 이 사건을 어떻게 접하게 됐나요? 이 내용은 제출되지 않았습니다.
When I was on this case,
제가 이 사건을 맡았을 때,
my friend who worked at a karaoke bar in Suwon said
수원 노래방에서 일하던 친구가 그러더군요
a worker there went missing out of the blue like this.
거기 직원이 이렇게 갑자기 실종됐어요.
What's your take on this?
이에 대해 어떻게 생각하시나요?
What I think doesn't matter.
내가 생각하는 것은 중요하지 않습니다.
I'm just a cop.
나는 단지 경찰일 뿐입니다.
I investigate when I get the order.
주문을 받으면 조사합니다.
And I don't when there's none.
그리고 사람이 없을 때는 안 해요.
You're a detective. You have no hunches?
당신은 형사입니다. 예감이 없나요?
Show me that you're at least trying to open this case.
최소한 이 사건을 열려고 한다는 걸 보여주세요.
There was a time
시간이 있었다
when I had to pay a hefty price
큰 대가를 치러야 했을 때
because of my hunches.
내 직감 때문에.
So I'm careful with everything.
그래서 매사에 조심스럽습니다.
-Okay. You can leave now. -Okay.
-좋아요. 지금 떠나셔도 됩니다. -좋아요.
SUPERINTENDENT HEO GIL-PYO
허길표 교육감
Well, both of the missing women
음, 실종된 두 여자 모두
were in the same line of work.
같은 일을 하고 있었어요.
I couldn't find any connections
어떤 연결도 찾을 수 없었습니다
other than their profession.
그들의 직업 외에.
Then…
그 다음에???
is it possible that there was no motive behind these cases?
이 사건 뒤에 동기가 없었을 가능성이 있습니까 ?
Is that your hunch?
그게 당신의 직감인가요?
Well, every detective has a hunch.
글쎄, 모든 형사는 직감을 가지고 있습니다.
Go.
가다.
This way.
이 방법.
Hello.
안녕하세요.
YEONGTONG-GU, SUWON, GYEONGGI PROVINCE
경기도 수원시 영통구
SHIN MI-JUNG'S HOUSE
신미정의 집
You guys still haven't found her?
아직도 그 사람을 못 찾았나요?
Maybe something really happened to her
어쩌면 그녀에게 정말로 무슨 일이 일어났을지도 모르지
if even you guys can't find her.
너희들도 그녀를 찾을 수 없다면.
That's not necessarily true.
반드시 그런 것은 아닙니다.
We're here to check a few things.
우리는 몇 가지 사항을 확인하기 위해 왔습니다.
Why come here twice
왜 여기 두번이나 와?
if this wasn't serious?
이게 심각한 게 아니라면?
Did she pay rent monthly?
그녀는 매달 집세를 냈나요?
She paid me monthly.
그녀는 나에게 매달 돈을 지불했습니다.
If you couldn't reach her since February,
2월 이후로 그녀에게 연락이 되지 않았다면,
she must be behind on rent for three months.
그녀는 3개월 동안 임대료를 연체해야 합니다 .
Yes. But I can just deduct her rent
예. 하지만 난 그냥 그녀의 집세를 공제할 수 있어
from the initial deposit she made.
그녀가 낸 초기 예금에서.
I just hope she's okay.
나는 그녀가 괜찮기를 바랍니다.
So no one came after our visit?
그럼 우리가 방문한 후에 아무도 오지 않았나요?
Hey.
여기요.
Gosh.
이런.
She's been my tenant
그녀는 내 세입자였어
for the past three years.
지난 3년 동안.
And I haven't seen her
그리고 난 그녀를 본 적이 없어요
bringing people here.
사람들을 여기로 데려옵니다.
She even stayed here during the holidays.
그녀는 휴일에도 여기에 머물렀다.
HERO KARAOKE BAR
히어로 가라오케 바
SHIN MI-JUNG, NO FAMILY, CASE NOT FILED
신미정, 가족 없음, 사건 미제출
MISSING PERSON
실종자
SING SING KARAOKE HOSTESSES ALWAYS AVAILABLE
SING SING 노래방 호스트는 항상 대기 중입니다.
Yes, come in.
응, 들어와.
Please call Song Ha-young.
송하영에게 전화주세요.
Inspector Song?
송 검사님?
I read the article and heard stories.
기사를 읽고 이야기를 들었습니다.
He has a knack for identifying connections between cases.
그는 사건들 사이의 연관성을 찾아내는 재주를 가지고 있습니다 .
Hey.
여기요.
You really don't think it's a missing person's case?
정말 실종자 사건이 아니라고 생각하시나요 ?
Well, we have no concrete proof yet,
글쎄요, 아직 구체적인 증거는 없습니다.
but my hunch says otherwise.
하지만 내 직감은 그렇지 않다고 말합니다.
If that's your hunch, it's probably right.
그게 당신의 직감이라면 아마 맞을 겁니다.
Mr. Heo, to what do I owe the pleasure of this call?
허 선생님, 제가 이 전화를 받게 된 것은 무엇 때문입니까?
Hey, how have you been?
안녕하세요, 잘 지내셨나요?
It took you this long to think of me?
나를 생각하는 데 이렇게 오랜 시간이 걸렸나요?
I just faxed something over to you.
방금 당신에게 팩스로 뭔가를 보냈습니다.
It's a missing person's case. Can you look into it?
실종자 사건입니다. 좀 살펴보실 수 있나요?
Of course, you wouldn't call me for no reason.
물론 아무 이유 없이 나에게 전화하지는 않을 것이다.
A missing karaoke bar employee? Is this the case?
실종된 노래방 직원? 이것이 사실입니까?
No. We did receive a report for that one.
아니요. 우리는 그에 대한 보고서를 받았습니다.
Apparently, there's an unreported case.
보고되지 않은 사건이 있는 것 같습니다.
"Apparently"?
"보기에"?
The person has no family or friends, and no one can reach her.
그 사람에게는 가족도 친구도 없고, 누구도 그 사람에게 연락할 수 없습니다.
What about this case?
이 경우는 어떻습니까?
Both missing women
실종된 두 여성 모두
worked at karaoke bars.
노래방에서 일했다.
When the Special Crime Squad was all lost, you guys said
특수수사대가 모두 사라졌을 때 너희들은 말했다
cases with more than two common things may be connected.
두 가지 이상의 공통점이 있는 경우는 연결될 수 있습니다.
These could be like the motiveless crimes you mentioned.
이것은 당신이 언급한 동기 없는 범죄와 같을 수 있습니다 .
Can you go check with Inspector Song?
송 경위한테 가서 확인해 볼 수 있나요?
Ha-young can't go.
하영이는 못 가요.
This is how you treat me now?
지금 나를 이렇게 대하는 거야?
You're hurting my feelings here.
당신 때문에 내 감정이 상하고 있어요.
I'll go and check.
가서 확인해 볼게요.
Right, everyone says your team is in high demand now.
맞아요, 다들 지금 당신 팀에 수요가 많다고 하더라고요.
I'll look into it and call you back.
제가 알아보고 다시 전화드리겠습니다.
Okay.
좋아요.
Was that Superintendent Heo at Gyeonggi Police Agency?
경기경찰청 허경경이었나 ?
Yes.
예.
I guess he hasn't heard about Inspector Song yet.
아직 송경사에 대해서는 들어보지 못한 것 같아요 .
He's at Gyeonggi Agency now,
지금은 경기사무소에 계시고,
so he wouldn't know unless he looked into it.
그래서 그는 그것을 조사하지 않으면 알 수 없었습니다 .
This is a missing person's case.
실종자 사건입니다.
Let's check the area, her movements, and the time of the incident.
사건 발생 장소와 동선, 시간 등을 확인해 보자 .
Yes, sir.
알겠습니다.
You're doing great.
당신은 잘하고 있습니다.
Let's try that one more time.
한 번 더 시도해 보겠습니다.
Neuroparalysis?
신경마비?
When the fractures occurred at the time of the accident,
사고 당시 골절이 발생했을 때 ,
some of the nerves around the bones were damaged.
뼈 주변의 일부 신경이 손상되었습니다.
Thankfully, he can move his toes a little,
다행히 발가락을 조금 움직일 수는 있지만
and there isn't a complete loss of sensation,
감각이 완전히 상실된 것도 아니고 ,
so I'd say it's partial paralysis.
그래서 부분마비라고 말하고 싶습니다.
In cases like this,
이런 경우
he could recover through rehabilitative therapy.
재활치료를 통해 회복할 수 있었습니다 .
The Seoul Metropolitan Police Agency
서울경찰청
transferred gang members who had been
이전된 갱단
embezzling cash through an illegal casino
불법 카지노를 통한 현금 횡령
to the prosecution.
검찰에
We wrapped up another case.
우리는 또 다른 사건을 마무리했습니다.
Good work, everyone.
모두들 수고했어요.
How about a team dinner?
팀 저녁식사 어때요?
You want to drink, don't you? Sit down already.
술 마시고 싶지 않나요? 벌써 앉으세요.
The case isn't closed
사건이 종결되지 않았습니다
until the trial is over.
재판이 끝날 때까지.
I told them to contact us if they need more evidence.
증거가 더 필요하면 연락하라고 했어요 .
Okay.
좋아요.
The gift certificates they received were used…
받은 상품권이 사용되었나요???
Right. Shouldn't we visit Inspector Song in the hospital?
오른쪽. 병원에 있는 송 경위를 찾아가면 안 될까요 ?
We haven't seen him since he moved to the general ward, right?
일반병실로 옮긴 이후로 한 번도 본 적이 없지요 ?
That's right.
좋아요.
GYEONGGI PROVINCIAL POLICE AGENCY
경기지방경찰청
Look at you.
당신을 보면.
Salute, Superintendent Heo Gil-pyo.
허길표 교육감님, 경례합니다.
Did you really come alone?
정말 혼자 오셨나요?
Why? Am I not good enough?
왜? 나는 충분하지 않은가?
I trained Korea's first criminal profiler.
저는 한국 최초의 범죄 프로파일러를 양성했습니다.
I'm in high demand.
나는 수요가 많다.
Goodness. Don't be so difficult.
선량. 너무 어렵게 생각하지 마세요.
This is so cool.
너무 멋져.
Oh, there he is.
아, 저기 있어요.
This is Chief Park of the Serious Crime Unit.
중대범죄수사대 박과장입니다 .
You know him, right?
그 사람 알지?
-Yes, we've met. -It's been a while.
- 네, 만났어요. -오랜만이야.
Take a seat.
앉아 요.
Are you in charge of this case?
이 사건 담당이신가요?
No, Anyang Police Station is in charge,
아니요, 안양경찰서가 담당하고 있으며,
but it's a little strange.
하지만 좀 이상해요.
As for the unreported case in Suwon, she has no family.
신고되지 않은 수원 사례의 경우 가족이 없다.
That's right. That was probably why no one reported.
좋아요. 그래서 아무도 신고하지 않았나 보다.
What's going on?
무슨 일이야?
Don't tell me…
말하지 마세요???
No, right?
권리 없다?
Hey, I'm still new here.
안녕하세요, 저는 아직 이곳에 온 지 얼마 되지 않았습니다.
Isn't that why you got in touch with me?
그래서 나한테 연락한 거 아냐?
I'll go check the scene first.
먼저 현장 확인하러 가겠습니다.
I'll go with you.
나는 당신과 함께 갈 것이다.
Slowly.
느리게.
Inspector Song.
송 검사님.
You came again.
당신은 다시 왔습니다.
Yes. Here, it's just something small.
예. 여기, 그것은 단지 작은 것입니다.
My gosh, you always bring something.
맙소사, 당신은 항상 뭔가를 가져옵니다.
Where can I put this?
이것을 어디에 놓을 수 있나요?
You can put it over there.
거기에 놓으시면 됩니다.
I'll leave you to talk. Since you're here,
얘기 좀 하도록 놔두겠습니다. 당신이 여기 있기 때문에,
I should step out for lunch.
점심 먹으러 나가야겠어요.
You didn't have to come all the way here.
여기까지 올 필요는 없었어요.
I heard you were undergoing rehabilitation.
재활치료를 받고 있다고 들었습니다 .
How are you feeling?
기분이 어때요?
Not bad.
나쁘지 않다.
Make yourselves at home.
집처럼 편안하게 지내세요.
I'll leave you to talk.
얘기 좀 하도록 놔두겠습니다.
Please stay. We'll leave soon.
머물러주세요. 우리는 곧 떠날 것이다.
You'll feel more comfortable without me.
나 없이도 당신은 더 편안해질 것입니다.
No, ma'am. That's not why we're here.
아니요, 부인. 그것이 우리가 여기 있는 이유가 아닙니다.
Yes, just stay.
응, 그냥 있어.
I want to step out for lunch.
점심 먹으러 나가고 싶어요.
-All right, then. -Enjoy your lunch.
- 그럼요. -점심 맛있게 드세요.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
Oh, let me.
아, 할게요.
I can do it by myself. Thank you.
나는 그것을 혼자서 할 수 있다. 감사합니다.
You're doing much better now.
이제 당신은 훨씬 더 잘 지내고 있습니다.
Oh, we came to see you when you were in the ICU.
아, 우리는 당신이 중환자실에 있을 때 당신을 만나러 왔습니다 .
That was when Captain Yoon and I met your mother.
그때 윤 선장과 내가 네 어머니를 만났던 거야.
Get better soon,
곧 좋아질,
so we can work together again.
그래서 우리는 다시 함께 일할 수 있습니다.
Yes, you're in high demand at the moment.
네, 지금은 수요가 많습니다.
The Behavioral Analysis Team was already very busy,
행동분석팀은 이미 매우 바쁜 시간을 보냈고,
but Chief Kook takes care of everything by himself now,
그런데 지금은 국과장님 혼자서 모든 일을 다 하시고 ,
so he's always swamped these days.
그래서 그는 요즘 항상 푹 빠져 있어요.
But you're almost fully recovered now.
하지만 이제 거의 완전히 회복되셨습니다.
You should be able to return to work very soon.
당신은 곧 직장에 복귀할 수 있을 것입니다 .
I don't intend on going back.
나는 돌아갈 생각이 없습니다.
As you can see, it's a quiet area.
보시다시피 조용한 지역이에요.
Most customers of this karaoke bar are people who live in the area.
이 노래방의 고객 대부분은 이 지역에 거주하는 사람들입니다.
I don't see any security cameras.
보안 카메라가 보이지 않습니다.
That's right.
좋아요.
The local precinct already questioned every customer who visited that day
해당 지역에서는 이미 그날 방문한 모든 고객에게 질문을 던졌습니다.
but found nothing.
하지만 아무것도 발견하지 못했습니다.
But her phone…
그런데 그 사람 전화???
On the map, you'll see Daejong Lake.
지도에는 대종호가 보입니다.
TOJUNG-DONG
토중동
DAEJONG LAKE
대전호수
Daejong Lake? It's like a recreation area.
대종호? 휴양지같네요.
It's estimated she went missing at around 1 a.m.,
새벽 1시쯤 실종된 것으로 추정되는데 ,
so she didn't go there to hang out.
그래서 그녀는 거기에 놀러 가지 않았습니다.
Nothing was caught on the security camera.
보안 카메라에는 아무것도 포착되지 않았습니다.
Any possibility of suicide?
자살 가능성은 없나요?
The divers already searched the entire lake
잠수부들은 이미 호수 전체를 수색했습니다
but found nothing.
하지만 아무것도 발견하지 못했습니다.
She didn't commit suicide.
그녀는 자살하지 않았습니다.
And the thing is,
그리고 문제는,
the person she last spoke to
그 사람이 마지막으로 통화한 사람
was her daughter.
그녀의 딸이었습니다.
She told her she'd pick up fried chicken and head home.
그녀는 프라이드치킨을 사서 집으로 가겠다고 말했습니다.
You wouldn't be able to hail a taxi here.
여기서는 택시를 탈 수 없습니다.
She probably took a bus at that stop.
아마 그 정류장에서 버스를 탔을 거예요.
Oh, right.
아, 그렇죠.
We already looked into it and even interviewed the driver
이미 알아보고 기사님 인터뷰까지 했는데요
who drove the last bus that night,
그날 밤 마지막 버스를 운전한 사람,
and she wasn't on the bus.
그리고 그녀는 버스에 없었어요.
And the location where her phone last pinged
그리고 그녀의 휴대폰이 마지막으로 핑을 울린 위치
is far from the bus route.
버스 노선과는 거리가 멀다.
Then how did she get there?
그러면 그녀는 거기 어떻게 갔나요?
She must've walked or…
그녀는 걸어갔나 봐요, 아니면???
Perhaps abducted?
아마도 납치된 걸까요?
-Hello. -I guess it's your day off.
-안녕하세요. - 쉬는 날이신가 봐요.
-Yes. Your soybean paste stew was so good. -I see.
-예. 된장찌개 너무 맛있었어요. -알겠어요.
-Really? I'll make it again. -Thank you. Goodbye.
-정말? 나는 다시 그것을 만들 것이다. -감사합니다. 안녕히 가세요.
Have a good day.
좋은 하루 보내세요.
MISSING PERSON
실종자
Her family must be so worried.
그녀의 가족은 너무 걱정했을 것입니다.
MISSING PERSON, PLEASE FIND MY MOTHER
실종자, 어머니를 찾아주세요
Song Ha-young is doing well, right?
송하영 잘 지내죠?
I've been meaning to get in touch, but I've been too busy.
연락을 하려고 했는데 너무 바빠서요.
I thought he'd come with you.
나는 그가 당신과 함께 올 것이라고 생각했습니다.
Ha-young is…
하영은???
Did he not want to come because of me?
나 때문에 오기 싫은 거였어?
-You know how he is, right? -I sure do.
- 그 사람 어떤지 아시죠? -꼭 그리하겠습니다.
He doesn't hold grudges.
그는 원한을 품지 않습니다.
He probably doesn't care what I'm up to.
그 사람은 아마 내가 무슨 일을 하고 있는지 관심도 없을 거예요.
If you're curious, you could reach out to him first.
궁금하다면 먼저 그에게 연락해 보세요.
Right. I'm sure I'll see him soon anyway.
오른쪽. 어쨌든 나는 그를 곧 보게 될 것이라고 확신한다.
Time will fly by.
시간이 빨리 지나갈 것입니다.
And you may never get a chance.
그리고 당신은 결코 기회를 얻지 못할 수도 있습니다.
Sorry?
죄송합니다?
Let's head over to Daejong Lake.
대종호로 가보자.
Nam Ki-Tae, the suspect in the Southwest Serial Murder Case,
서남권 연쇄살인사건 용의자 남기태
showed no remorse for his actions during his first trial last month.
지난 달 첫 번째 재판에서 자신의 행동에 대해 전혀 후회하지 않았습니다 .
His attitude enraged the bereaved families and…
그의 태도는 유족들을 분노하게 만들었고???
Why would I feel remorse?
왜 후회하게 될까요?
I'm not sorry at all. I don't even feel guilty.
전혀 미안하지 않아요. 죄책감조차 느끼지 않습니다.
I'm so sorry, Hwa-yeon.
정말 미안해요, 화연씨.
I'm sorry, Hwa-yeon.
미안해, 화연아.
At that intersection up ahead,
저 앞쪽 교차로에서
the road splits up into the victim's home and Daejong Lake.
길은 피해자 집과 대종호로 갈라진다.
If you turn left and find Daejong Lake.
좌회전하면 대종호가 나옵니다.
If she wanted to go home, she should've taken a right.
집에 가고 싶었다면 오른쪽으로 갔어야 했어요.
The location of the phone the missing person pinged
실종자가 핑한 휴대폰 위치
right there on the left
바로 거기 왼쪽에
and turned off as she went for the lake.
그녀가 호수로 가면서 전원을 껐습니다.
Let's say she was abducted.
그녀가 납치되었다고 가정 해 봅시다.
If she was forced to get in his car, he would've taken her phone first.
만약 그녀가 강제로 그의 차에 타야 한다면 그는 먼저 그녀의 휴대폰을 가져갔을 것입니다.
But the phone of an abducted woman was
그런데 납치된 여성의 전화는
turned on until she got here.
그녀가 여기 올 때까지 켜져 있었어.
The last person she talked to was her daughter.
그녀가 마지막으로 이야기를 나눈 사람은 딸이었습니다.
After she left the karaoke bar, she didn't make any calls.
그녀는 노래방을 떠난 후 어떤 전화도 걸지 않았습니다.
Maybe she volunteered to hop in.
아마도 그녀는 자원해서 타려고 했을지도 모릅니다.
Not unless she knew him.
그녀가 그를 알지 않는 한 그렇지 않습니다.
She wouldn't get into a random car.
그녀는 임의의 차에 타지 않을 것입니다.
Did you question her associates?
그녀의 동료들에게 질문했나요?
Yes.
예.
DAEJONG LAKE
대전호수
GUKIL HOSPITAL
국일병원
They came and visited you twice
그들은 당신을 두 번이나 방문했습니다
even when you were in the ICU.
심지어 중환자실에 있었을 때도요.
You didn't know?
몰랐어요?
A few more visited you other than them.
그들 말고도 몇 사람이 더 당신을 방문했습니다.
You weren't aware?
몰랐나요?
Not just Chief Young-soo?
영수과장님뿐만 아니라요?
Chief Young-soo stops by very often.
영수 과장이 자주 들른다.
Some younger people came too.
젊은 분들도 오셨어요.
A woman and a man.
여자와 남자.
I see.
알겠어요.
And there were other people from the Seoul Agency,
그리고 서울청 관계자 분들도 계셨고 ,
someone on the older side.
나이가 좀 많은 사람.
Then other people
그러면 다른 사람들은
who said they're your colleagues lined up to visit you,
누가 당신을 방문하기 위해 줄을 서 있는 당신의 동료라고 하더군요 .
even after you were moved here and bedbound.
당신이 여기로 옮겨져 침대에 누워 있는 후에도 말이죠 .
Even as you were in bed,
당신이 침대에 누워 있는 동안에도,
all of your colleagues flooded in and visited you,
당신의 동료들이 모두 몰려와서 당신을 방문했습니다.
so I was really glad.
그래서 정말 기뻤어요.
You didn't know if your son was going to wake up,
아들이 깨어날지 모르셨죠 ?
but you were glad?
그런데 기뻤어?
Why wouldn't I know that?
나는 왜 그것을 몰랐을까요?
I knew you would wake up.
나는 당신이 깨어날 것이라는 것을 알았습니다.
How? Even the doctor didn't.
어떻게? 심지어 의사도 그러지 않았어요.
I'm your mom.
나는 당신의 엄마입니다.
GUKIL HOSPITAL
국일병원
Ha-young is asleep, right?
하영이는 자고 있지 않나요?
Yes, he fell asleep half an hour ago.
네, 그는 30분 전에 잠들었습니다.
I see. How was he today?
알겠어요. 오늘 그는 어땠나요?
His rehab is going well,
재활은 잘 진행되고 있고,
and he's recovering quickly too.
그리고 그 사람도 빨리 회복하고 있어요.
Right, Captain Yoon and Detective Nam stopped by this afternoon.
그렇죠, 오늘 오후에는 윤 대위와 남 형사가 들렀습니다.
Goodness, he must've felt awkward.
맙소사, 그는 분명 어색함을 느꼈을 것입니다.
Only on the outside. He's not like that on the inside.
외부에서만. 그 사람 속은 그런 사람이 아니거든요.
It's not like I've known him only for a couple of days.
내가 그 사람을 알고 지낸 지 며칠밖에 안 된 것 같아요 .
I can tell by his face.
나는 그의 얼굴을 통해 알 수 있습니다.
Chief Young-soo, you should see Ha-young before you leave.
영수과장님, 떠나기 전에 하영이를 만나보세요.
I still can't muster up the courage.
아직은 용기가 나지 않습니다.
Goodness.
선량.
MANYEON-DONG, GUNPO, GYEONGGI PROVINCE
경기도 군포시 만연동
Excuse me, may I ask you a question?
죄송한데 질문 하나 해도 될까요?
Oh, I'm not dangerous.
아, 난 위험하지 않아.
I wanted to ask you for directions.
나는 당신에게 길을 묻고 싶었습니다.
Sure.
확신하는.
I'm trying to go to Taepyeong Park. Which way do I need to go?
태평공원에 가려고 해요. 어느 쪽으로 가야 하나요?
It's probably closed right now.
지금은 아마 문을 닫은 것 같아요.
Oh, I'm not trying to go there.
아, 거기 가려고 하는 게 아닌데.
I'm going in that direction.
나는 그 방향으로 가고 있다.
I see.
알겠어요.
You can go down this way for about 900 meters.
이 길로 약 900m 정도 내려갈 수 있습니다 .
When you see a big barbecue place on the right, take a right.
오른쪽에 큰 바베큐장이 보이면 오른쪽으로 가세요.
Turn right at the barbecue place.
바비큐 장소에서 우회전하세요.
-Yes. And then… -One second.
-예. 그런 다음??? -일초.
I have a bad memory,
기억력이 안 좋아서,
so let me write it down.
그래서 적어 보겠습니다.
Hold on.
기다리다.
I don't have paper or a pen.
종이도 펜도 없어요.
It's not that confusing.
그다지 혼란스럽지 않습니다.
Turn right at the barbecue place, then the second--
바비큐 장소에서 오른쪽으로 돌아서 두 번째--
Where are you headed?
넌 어디로 가고 있니?
Me?
나?
If you don't mind, I can give you a ride.
괜찮으시다면 제가 태워드릴 수 있습니다.
The bus will be here soon. It's all right.
버스가 곧 여기에 올 거예요. 괜찮아요.
I'm driving down anyway.
어쨌든 난 운전해서 내려가는 중이야.
If you're going in the same direction, I'll give you a ride.
같은 방향으로 가신다면 제가 태워드리겠습니다.
No, I'm fine.
아냐 난 괜찮아.
I'm not dangerous, you know.
난 위험하지 않아요.
That's not why.
그런 이유는 아닙니다.
The bus stops near my house,
집 근처에 버스가 정차하고,
so I'm really fine.
그래서 저는 정말 괜찮아요.
Well, the world is now a dangerous place,
자, 이제 세상은 위험한 곳이 되었습니다.
so it's not easy to hop in, right?
그래서 타기가 쉽지 않죠?
No.
아니요.
When will the bus get here?
버스는 언제 여기에 도착하나요?
Is it the last bus?
마지막 버스인가요?
It's about time it came.
이제 올 시간이 되었습니다.
Did you miss the last one?
마지막을 놓쳤나요?
Then I can wait with you.
그럼 난 당신과 함께 기다릴 수 있습니다.
If you missed the last bus,
마지막 버스를 놓치셨다면,
I can give you a ride.
제가 태워드릴 수 있어요.
No, I'm really fine.
아니요, 저는 정말 괜찮아요.
No, I'll leave after I see you get on the bus.
아니요, 당신이 버스에 타는 걸 보고 나서 갈게요 .
The last bus left, right?
마지막 버스가 남았죠?
It's pretty late,
꽤 늦었는데,
so I have to get going too.
그러니까 나도 가야 해.
You really won't get in?
정말 안 들어갈 거예요?
Will you be okay?
괜찮으시겠어요?
I'll go, then.
그럼 난 갈게.
Then can you just tell me the directions once again?
그럼 길을 다시 한 번 알려 주시겠어요 ?
Go down this way, then at the barbecue…
이쪽으로 내려가서 바베큐로???
Why don't you just get in?
그냥 들어가보는 게 어때?
Why are you so anxious?
왜 그렇게 불안해?
Goodness, it must be cold.
맙소사, 추울 텐데.
Hop in.
올라 타다.
In that case, thank you.
그렇다면 감사합니다.
The bus is here. I'll take that.
버스가 여기 있어요. 내가 가져갈게.
Take a left at the second intersection.
두 번째 교차로에서 좌회전하세요.
Damn it.
젠장.
Damn it!
젠장!
That bus.
그 버스.
SEOUL METROPOLITAN POLICE AGENCY
서울지방경찰청
Can you check if there are any similar cases in the Gyeonggi area?
경기도에도 비슷한 사례가 있는지 확인해주실 수 있나요 ?
Yes.
예.
The first one wasn't even reported.
첫 번째는보고조차되지 않았습니다.
We can only speculate instead of investigating it.
우리는 그것을 조사하는 대신 추측만 할 수 있습니다 .
It's tough to be the judge just with that case.
그 사건만으로는 판사가 되기가 어렵습니다 .
Anyway, continue to check if there are any similar cases.
어쨌든 비슷한 사례가 있는지 계속 확인해보세요.
Okay.
좋아요.
-Captain Yoon. -Thank you.
-윤 선장. -감사합니다.
You're here.
너 여기 있네.
-Chief.
-셰프.
-Is that for me? -Yes.
- 그게 나를 위한 건가요? -예.
-Thank you. -Sure.
-감사합니다. -확신하는.
It feels like I'm on a break drinking coffee away from
멀리서 커피를 마시며 쉬는 듯한 느낌
the Wide-Area Investigation office.
광역조사실.
Coffee is about the only thing that can comfort people like us.
커피는 우리 같은 사람들을 위로할 수 있는 유일한 것입니다 .
So…
그래서???
is the Analysis Team working on a case?
분석팀이 사건을 조사하고 있나요?
Oh, it's Gil-pyo.
아, 길표예요.
Superintendent Heo?
허 교육감?
Well, it's a missing case of karaoke bar employees.
참, 노래방 직원의 실종사건입니다 .
He said there was one each in February and April.
2월과 4월에 각각 한 번씩 있었다고 하더군요 .
He wanted our opinion, so I went to Gyeonggi Agency yesterday.
우리의 의견을 원하셔서 어제 경기청을 방문했습니다.
Did you go alone?
혼자 가셨나요?
Yes, it's not even that far.
네, 그리 멀지도 않습니다.
But what do you mean the first case
그런데 첫 번째 경우는 무슨 뜻인가요?
was not reported?
신고되지 않았나요?
I overheard you on the phone.
나는 전화로 당신의 말을 우연히 들었습니다.
While they investigated the missing case from April,
지난 4월부터 실종사건을 조사하던 중 ,
they found an unreported missing case,
신고되지 않은 실종 사건을 발견했고,
because she lived alone without any family.
가족도 없이 혼자 살았기 때문이다 .
I see.
알겠어요.
Right, so what brings you here?
그렇군요, 그래서 당신을 여기로 데려온 이유는 무엇입니까?
Detective Nam and I went to visit Inspector Song yesterday.
남 형사와 저는 어제 송 형사를 만나러 갔습니다.
I heard.
들었어.
He seemed very exhausted.
그는 매우 지친 것 같았습니다.
I think…
제 생각에는???
he needs some time to himself.
그에게는 혼자만의 시간이 필요해요.
RESIGNATION LETTER
사직서
I don't want to go back.
나는 돌아가고 싶지 않다.
I see.
알겠어요.
Don't think about anything else,
다른 것은 생각하지 마세요.
and just focus on your health while you stay in the hospital.
병원에 계시는 동안 건강에만 집중하세요 .
I'm spending
나는 지출하고있다
a lot more time with my mother
어머니와 더 많은 시간을 보내세요
since I was hospitalized.
병원에 입원한 이후로.
We're having meals together.
우리는 함께 식사를 하고 있어요.
And we're talking a lot more.
그리고 우리는 더 많은 이야기를 나누고 있습니다.
I can't even remember the last time I had a normal day like this.
이렇게 평범한 하루를 보낸 게 언제인지 기억도 나지 않습니다 .
I realized that having a normal life like this was the joy of life.
이렇게 평범한 삶을 사는 것이 삶의 즐거움이라는 것을 깨달았습니다 .
I've been dealing with only evil, intelligent criminals.
나는 사악하고 지능적인 범죄자들만 상대해 왔습니다 .
I guess I was fed up with them.
나는 그들에게 싫증이 났던 것 같아요.
-Captain Kook. -Yes.
-국 선장님. -예.
Do you think I was only trying to put myself
내가 내 자신만 담으려고 했다고 생각하나요?
in their shoes?
그들의 신발에?
To be honest, what scared me the most
솔직히 가장 무서웠던 건
was the anxiety
불안이었어.
that there might be a different side of me I was not aware of.
내가 모르는 또 다른 나의 모습이 있을지도 모른다는 것 .
I was scared
난 겁이 났어요
that even I might turn into them.
나조차도 그들로 변할 수 있기를.
For now,
지금으로서는,
don't let these thoughts get to you. Okay?
이런 생각이 당신에게 닿도록 두지 마십시오. 좋아요?
Just look after yourself and rest.
그냥 자신을 돌보고 휴식을 취하세요.
I'll get going.
나는 갈 것이다.
And I will hold on to this for now.
그리고 나는 지금 이 일을 계속할 것입니다.
Captain Kook.
국 선장.
I don't want to go back.
나는 돌아가고 싶지 않다.
-Chief Kook. -Yes.
- 국과장님. -예.
I'm here to talk about that.
나는 그것에 대해 이야기하기 위해 여기에 있습니다.
It's fine. Woo-ju knows everything.
괜찮아. 우주는 모든 것을 알고 있다.
Okay.
좋아요.
You watched the interview. So you know
인터뷰를 시청하셨습니다. 그러니까 알잖아
that they're beyond our imagination.
우리의 상상을 초월한다는 것입니다.
Those monsters dump out
그 괴물들은 덤벼들지
a different kind of trash from the interrogation.
심문과는 다른 종류의 쓰레기 .
And handling this trash
그리고 이 쓰레기를 처리하는 중
isn't easy.
쉽지 않습니다.
Right.
오른쪽.
And that probably exploded.
그리고 그것은 아마도 폭발했을 것입니다.
He needs time to empty it out too.
그에게도 비울 시간이 필요하다.
Time to empty it out…
비워야 할 시간???
You need to take it easy too, Captain Yoon.
윤대위 님도 정신차려야 합니다 .
When people keep running without a break,
사람들이 쉬지 않고 계속 달릴 때,
they always trip over and explode.
그들은 항상 넘어져서 폭발합니다.
So…
그래서???
what do you plan to do about Inspector Song?
송 경위는 어떻게 할 생각이에요 ?
I need to wait.
기다려야 해요.
After everything he's been through,
그가 모든 일을 겪은 후에,
I couldn't push him again
난 그 사람을 다시는 밀어낼 수 없었어
because I felt responsible
책임감을 느꼈기 때문에
for his current state.
그의 현재 상태를 위해.
PUNGYEON-DONG, ANYANG, GYEONGGI PROVINCE
경기도 안양시 풍연동
KARAOKE
노래방
You're not going to sing?
노래 안 할 거예요?
No. Let's just talk.
아뇨. 그냥 얘기 좀 합시다.
It's a waste of money.
그것은 돈 낭비입니다.
Why don't you sing a song?
노래를 불러보는 게 어때요?
I would rather talk to you
차라리 너랑 얘기하고 싶어
than sing a song.
노래를 부르는 것보다.
Sure. I'll turn off the music.
확신하는. 음악을 끌게요.
Shall we go for another round?
한 라운드 더 가볼까요?
-What are you doing? -It's fine. Don't be like that.
-뭐하세요? -괜찮아. 그렇게 하지 마십시오.
Stop it.
그만해요.
Get your hands off me.
나한테서 손 떼세요.
Stop it!
그만해요!
Damn it!
젠장!
What the hell are you doing?
당신은 뭐 해요?
Hey.
여기요.
Open up. Unlock the door!
열어라. 문을 열어라!
You!
너!
You're ruining my good mood.
당신이 내 좋은 기분을 망치고 있어요.
GUKIL HOSPITAL
국일병원
SONG HA-YOUNG
송하영
Excuse me.
실례합니다.
This is Detective Song Ha-young's room, right?
여기가 송하영 형사님 방 맞죠?
Yes, it is. Why do you ask?
예, 그렇습니다. 왜 물어보나요?
Could you give this to Detective Song?
이것을 송형사에게 전해 주시겠습니까?
Sure.
확신하는.
VOLUNTEER
자원 봉사자
Hey, Ha-young.
안녕하세요, 하영님.
I think she works here as a volunteer.
내 생각엔 그녀가 여기서 자원봉사자로 일하는 것 같아요.
But she told me to give this to you and left.
그런데 그 분이 이걸 너한테 주라고 하고 가셨다.
A volunteer?
자원봉사자?
Yes. Open it. I'm curious to see what it is.
예. 열어 봐. 나는 그것이 무엇인지 궁금해합니다.
Goodness. What's all this?
선량. 이게 다 뭐야?
She must be an excellent cook.
그녀는 훌륭한 요리사임에 틀림없어요.
Goodness. There's a card too.
선량. 카드도 있어요.
-Here. -Right.
-여기. -오른쪽.
Goodness. I can't believe this.
선량. 나는 이것을 믿을 수 없다.
SOS. I can't handle Chief Kook's jokes by myself.
SOS. 국과장님의 농담을 혼자서 감당할 수가 없어요 .
I hope you get well and come back soon.
몸을 회복하고 곧 돌아오길 바랍니다.
How's the rehab going?
재활은 잘 진행되고 있나요?
I'm sorry for not visiting you often.
자주 찾아뵙지 못해 죄송합니다.
Inspector Song, it's winter now.
송 경위님, 이제 겨울이에요.
It's gotten cold.
추워졌어요.
Don't catch a cold, and take care of yourself.
감기 걸리지 마시고 몸 조심하세요.
RESIGNATION LETTER
사직서
INVESTIGATIVE POINTS
조사 포인트
THE SUSPECT LIVES ALONE
용의자는 혼자 산다
Think only about the victims…
피해자만 생각하세요???
and the bereaved families.
그리고 유족
TOJUNG-DONG, ANYANG, GYEONGGI PROVINCE
경기도 안양시 토중동
Sir, I want to touch that!
선생님, 저거 만지고 싶어요!
Which one? That one?
어느 것? 하나?
That one over there.
저기 있는 것.
Come here.
이리 오세요.
How pretty.
얼마나 예쁜.
Is that all?
그게 다야?
-No. I want to touch this too! -This one?
-아니요. 나도 이거 만지고 싶다! -이 하나?
-Right? -Yes.
-오른쪽? -예.
EMERGENCY MEDICAL CENTER
응급 의료 센터
You seem to be doing much better now.
이제 당신은 훨씬 더 잘 지내고 있는 것 같습니다.
Yes, thanks to you.
네, 고마워요.
That's good to hear.
좋은 소식이네요.
Thank you for the food.
음식을 주셔서 감사합니다.
I really enjoyed it.
나는 그것을 정말로 즐 겼어.
I should've thanked you sooner.
좀 더 일찍 감사 인사를 했어야 했는데.
It was long ago,
오래전 일이었는데,
so I didn't think you'd remember me
그래서 당신이 나를 기억하지 못할 거라고 생각했어요
since you work on so many cases.
당신이 너무 많은 사건을 맡으니까요.
I remember everything.
나는 모든 것을 기억합니다.
I remember Ms. Choi Hwa-yeon…
최화연씨를 기억하시나요???
and you too.
당신도.
It's just that
바로 그거야
I didn't have the courage.
용기가 없었어요.
To face…
직면하기???
the victims
피해자
or their families again.
아니면 그 가족들이 다시.
I felt the same way.
나도 같은 느낌을 받았다.
When I think about the scumbag who did that to Hwa-yeon,
화연한테 그런 짓을 한 그 쓰레기를 생각하면
I still want him to suffer the same.
나는 아직도 그 사람이 똑같은 고통을 받기를 바랍니다.
Whenever I'm reminded that he's doing just fine in jail,
그 사람이 감옥에서 잘 지내고 있다는 생각이 들 때마다
I feel so resentful.
정말 분개해요.
I just want to follow Hwa-yeon and die too.
나도 그냥 화연이 따라가서 죽고싶다.
My life has been so miserable.
내 인생은 너무 비참했습니다.
To tell you the truth, I couldn't bring myself
사실을 말하자면, 난 정신을 차릴 수가 없었어
to say hello to you when I first saw you here
여기서 처음 봤을 때 인사하려고
because all the horrible memories came rushing back.
끔찍한 기억이 모두 되살아났기 때문이다.
I had nightmares for days.
나는 며칠 동안 악몽을 꾸었습니다.
I thought maybe I should stop
그만둬야 하지 않을까 생각했어요
volunteering here.
여기서 자원봉사를 해요.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
Why are you sorry?
너가 왜 미안해?
I should thank you if anything.
있다면 감사해야 할 것 같습니다.
That's why I still had the handkerchief.
그래서 아직도 손수건을 갖고 있었던 거다.
One day, I saw it again
어느날 또 봤는데
and realized
그리고 깨달았다
that I had been able to hold out
내가 버틸 수 있었던 건
thanks to everyone
모두에게 감사 드려요
who did their best for me and Hwa-yeon.
나와 화연이를 위해 최선을 다해준 사람.
And you're one of them.
그리고 당신도 그들 중 하나입니다.
Hold on a moment.
잠깐만 기다려.
-Where are you going? -I'll be right back.
-어디 가세요? - 금방 돌아올게요.
Just a moment.
잠시만.
I ran into you, so I couldn't prepare anything
너와 마주쳐 아무것도 준비하지 못했어
Here, take this and eat it.
자, 이것을 받아 먹어 보세요.
No, it's okay.
아니 괜찮아.
I bought it just now, so it's still warm.
지금 구입해서 아직 따뜻해요.
Then let's eat it together.
그럼 같이 먹자.
This is for your recovery
이것은 당신의 회복을 위한 것입니다.
and a small token of my gratitude.
그리고 작은 감사의 표시를 전합니다.
I read the newspaper articles.
나는 신문 기사를 읽었다.
Just like back then,
그때처럼,
you only think about the victims and their families.
피해자와 그 가족 들만 생각하는 거죠 .
-Thank you very much. -No problem.
-정말 감사합니다. -문제없어요.
Some of the bereaved manage to pluck up the courage to live on,
사별한 사람들 중 일부는 살아갈 용기를 얻었습니다.
but I'm sure some are still drowning in sorrow.
하지만 일부 사람들은 아직도 슬픔에 잠겨 있다고 확신합니다 .
Please help people like us,
우리 같은 사람들을 도와주세요.
so no one else
그러니 다른 사람은 없어
has to lose their loved ones like that.
사랑하는 사람을 그렇게 잃어야 해요.
Joy to the world, the Lord has come
세상은 기쁨이여, 주님이 오셨습니다
-Inspector Song! -Hey.
-송 경위님! -여기요.
-You woke him up. -I'm sorry.
-당신이 그를 깨웠어요. -죄송합니다.
It's okay. I had to get up anyway.
괜찮아요. 어쨌든 나는 일어나야만 했다.
-When did you get here? -Just now.
-언제 여기 왔니? -방금.
Here, this is for you.
여기, 이것은 당신을 위한 것입니다.
I picked out the best ones.
나는 가장 좋은 것을 골랐다.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
When will Chief Kook get here?
국과장님은 언제 오시나요?
I thought he was coming with you.
나는 그가 당신과 함께 올 것이라고 생각했습니다.
He'll be here later.
그 사람은 나중에 여기에 올 거예요.
-Have some. -Thank you.
- 좀 드세요. -감사합니다.
-You too, Reporter Choi.
-최 기자님도요.
You can go home soon, right?
이제 곧 집에 갈 수 있겠죠?
Yes, in two days.
네, 이틀 후에요.
After almost six months.
거의 6개월 후.
-How do you feel? -Is this an interview?
- 기분이 어떤가요? -이거 인터뷰야?
Come up with better questions.
더 나은 질문을 생각해 보세요.
Of course, he's excited.
물론 그는 신이 났습니다.
Then what will you do as soon as you get home?
그러면 집에 오자마자 무엇을 할 건가요 ?
I'm not sure.
잘 모르겠습니다.
I haven't really thought about it.
나는 그것에 대해 정말로 생각하지 않았습니다.
Wait, hold on!
잠깐만요!
Let's go eat something.
뭔가 먹으러 가자.
You want to eat again?
또 먹고 싶어?
You didn't have dinner?
저녁 안 드셨나요?
I did, but I'm hungry again.
그랬는데 또 배가 고프네요.
-It's winter, you know. -She eats a lot.
- 겨울이잖아요. -그녀는 많이 먹습니다.
-It's good to eat a lot. -Oh, Chief Kook.
- 많이 먹어도 좋아요. -아, 국과장님.
-You made it. -We waited for you until now.
-네가 해냈어. -우리는 지금까지 당신을 기다렸습니다.
-I see. You're leaving now? -Yes, we are.
-알겠어요. 지금 떠나는 건가요? -네, 우리는.
You're here.
너 여기 있네.
Hey.
여기요.
Get in, guys.
들어가세요 여러분.
I guess these guys kept you up. You should be in bed now.
이 사람들이 당신을 계속 유지했다고 생각합니다. 당신은 지금 침대에 누워 있어야합니다.
You just got here. Are you leaving right away?
당신은 방금 여기에 도착했습니다. 바로 출발하시나요?
Yes. I mean, no.
예. 내 말은, 아니.
Actually, I should get going. You need to go to bed.
사실, 난 가봐야 해. 잠자리에 드세요.
I'm glad to see you looking healthy. I'll be off, then.
건강하신 모습 보니 반갑습니다. 그럼 난 이만 갈게.
Bye.
안녕.
-See you in the office. -Okay, good night.
-사무실에서 봐요. -그래 잘 자.
What did Ha-young say just now?
방금 하영이가 뭐라고 말했어요?
"See you in the office."
"사무실에서 만나요."
What is it?
그것은 무엇입니까?
Excuse me, did you miss the bus just now?
실례합니다. 방금 버스를 놓쳤나요?
-Pardon? -It's cold.
-뭐라고요? -추워.
I can give you a ride.
제가 태워드릴 수 있어요.
I'm following the bus route anyway,
어쨌든 버스 노선을 따라가고 있어요.
so I can drop you off along the way.
그러니 내가 가는 길에 당신을 내려줄 수 있어요.
-This looks so good. -It looks amazing.
-아주 좋아 보이는군요. - 정말 놀랍네요.
Eat it with green onions. It's so good.
파와 함께 드세요. 너무 좋아요.
Inspector Song
송 경위
looked more high-spirited than ever before.
그 어느 때보다 더 씩씩해 보였다 .
I'm sure he's relieved that he can finally go home.
나는 그가 마침내 집에 갈 수 있다는 사실에 안도감을 느꼈을 것이라고 확신합니다 .
It must've been tough.
힘들었을 것 같아요.
Oh, Detective Nam.
아, 남 형사님.
What are you doing here?
여기서 뭐하는거야?
We met at Mapo Police Station and in front of Seoul HQ as well.
마포경찰서에서도 만났고 , 서울본사 앞에서도 만났습니다.
You remember me, right?
나를 기억하지?
I'm Reporter Choi Yoon-ji from Fact Today.
팩트투데이 최윤지 기자입니다.
That's right, Reporter Choi Yoon-ji.
맞습니다, 최윤지 기자입니다.
I'm Nam Il-young, Wide-Area Investigation Squad.
광역수사대 남일영 입니다 .
-Good to see you. -You're always so quick.
-만나서 반가워. - 당신은 항상 너무 빠르네요.
-Are you here alone? -I stopped by on my way home.
- 여기 혼자 오셨나요? - 집에 가는 길에 들렀어요.
I'm picking up my late-night snack.
나는 야식을 사러 가는 중이에요.
-Let's sit down. -Okay.
-앉자. -좋아요.
-We were going to order some drinks. -I see.
-우리는 음료수를 주문하려고 했어요. -알겠어요.
Excuse me, could we get two more servings?
실례합니다. 2인분만 더 주시겠어요?
My goodness.
이럴 수가.
I don't want to be a third wheel.
나는 세 번째 바퀴가되고 싶지 않습니다.
Gosh, no. We're just friends.
이런, 아니. 우리는 그저 친구 다.
-Don't even worry about it. -Oh, really?
-걱정하지 마세요. -오, 진짜?
You sure know how to enjoy beef intestines.
당신은 쇠고기 내장을 즐기는 방법을 확실히 알고 있습니다 .
BUS STOP GEUMCHAN VILLAGE
버스정류장 금찬마을
Thank you.
감사합니다.
Were you out with your friends?
친구들과 함께 있었나요?
Yes.
예.
I couldn't just pass by, looking at you freezing.
얼어붙은 너를 바라보며 그냥 지나칠 수가 없었다 .
Thank you.
감사합니다.
You can just drop me off along the way.
가는 길에 저를 내려주시면 됩니다.
It'll probably start snowing soon.
아마 곧 눈이 내리기 시작할 것 같아요.
We should help each other out, you know?
우리는 서로 도와야 해, 알지?
Who knows? Santa Claus may give us a gift.
누가 알아? 산타클로스는 우리에게 선물을 줄 수도 있습니다.
That's true.
그것은 사실이다.
You deserve a nice Christmas gift for this.
당신은 이것에 대한 좋은 크리스마스 선물을받을 자격이 있습니다.
Then how about you give me a gift?
그럼 나한테 선물을 주는 게 어때?
Sorry?
죄송합니다?
I want a gift.
나는 선물을 원한다.
Hey.
여기요.
I had fun thanks to you.
덕분에 즐거웠습니다.
CHIEF PARK DAE-WOONG
박대웅 수석
Hello?
안녕하세요?
Okay.
좋아요.
Superintendent Heo.
허 교육감.
Another girl has gone missing in Tojung-dong.
토중동에서 또 한 명의 소녀가 실종됐다 .
-Again? -I think it's the same guy.
-다시? - 같은 사람인 것 같아요.
Give Young-soo a call too.
영수한테도 전화해봐.
FEMALE COLLEGE STUDENT GOES MISSING IN GYEONGGI PROVINCE BEFORE CHRISTMAS
경기도 여대생, 크리스마스 앞두고 실종
-Chief. -Yes?
-셰프. -예?
We received a missing person's report from Tojung-dong, right?
토중동에서 실종자 신고가 접수됐죠 ?
Yes. Why do you ask?
예. 왜 물어보나요?
Yes, Chief Park?
응, 박과장?
Okay. I got it. I'm going to Gyeonggi Agency.
좋아요. 알겠어요. 경기 대리점으로 갑니다.
Okay, I'll see you later.
알겠습니다. 나중에 뵙겠습니다.
Yes, I'll head over right now.
네, 지금 바로 가겠습니다.
-Here's your receipt. -Oh, yes.
- 여기 영수증이 있어요. -바로 이거 야.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
I'll get a taxi for you. Go home first.
택시를 불러올게요. 먼저 집에 가세요.
Don't do that, I can take the bus.
그러지 마세요. 버스를 타면 돼요.
Taxis are more comfortable.
택시가 더 편해요.
All right, then. Thank you.
그럼요. 감사합니다.
Take it easy, okay?
진정하세요, 알았죠?
Yes, don't worry.
네, 걱정하지 마세요.
I'm so glad you're getting discharged.
퇴원하셔서 정말 다행이에요.
I won't scare you like that again. I'm sorry.
다시는 그런 식으로 겁을 주지 않을 거예요. 죄송합니다.
-Let me carry that. -It's fine.
-그것은 제가 가지고 가겠습니다. -괜찮아.
-I got it. -You're so stubborn.
-알겠어요. -당신은 너무 고집스럽군요.
-I told you to take it easy. -Let's go.
-편안하게 지내라고 했어요. -갑시다.
SEOUL METROPOLITAN POLICE AGENCY
서울지방경찰청
Inspector.
조사관.
-Are you feeling better? -Yes, I'm fine.
-기분이 좋아졌나요? -네, 괜찮아요.
Why did you come here instead of heading home?
집으로 가지 않고 왜 여기에 왔나요 ?
I'm good to work now.
나는 지금 일하기에 좋다.
Where's Chief Kook?
국과장님은 어디 계시나요?
He went to the Gyeonggi Agency.
경기청으로 갔습니다.
The Gyeonggi Police Agency?
경기경찰청?
Why did he go there?
그는 왜 거기에 갔습니까?
TRUSTWORTHY POLICE SAFE AND STRONG COUNTRY
신뢰할 수 있는 경찰 안전하고 강한 나라
There was a bus stop in front of the karaoke bar, right?
노래방 앞에 버스 정류장이 있었죠 ?
-Yes, there was. -Okay.
-네, 있었어요. -좋아요.
The missing person's job group is completely different though.
하지만 실종자의 직종은 전혀 다르다.
But the area is all very similar.
하지만 그 지역은 모두 매우 비슷합니다.
Hey, how did you know I was here?
야, 내가 여기 있는 걸 어떻게 알았어?
Are you feeling better?
기분이 나아졌나요?
Yes.
예.
-It's been a while. -Have you been well?
-오랜만이야. - 잘 지냈어요?
Woo-ju briefed me on the case when I got to the office.
내가 사무실에 도착하자 우주는 나에게 사건에 대해 설명했다 .
Can you explain the case to me in detail?
사건을 자세히 설명해 주실 수 있나요?
All right. As it was reported here,
괜찮은. 여기에 보도된 바와 같이,
a woman went missing from a karaoke bar in April.
지난 4월 노래방에서 한 여성이 실종됐다 .
But back in February,
그런데 지난 2월,
another employee from a karaoke bar
노래방의 다른 직원
went missing but it wasn't reported.
실종됐는데 신고가 안 됐어요.
Then two days ago, on the 23rd,
그러다가 이틀 전인 23일,
a female university student went missing from the same bus stop.
같은 버스 정류장에서 여대생이 실종됐다 .
I think it's the same perp for all three cases.
세 사건 다 같은 범인인 것 같아요 .
When we visited the crime scene for the case in April,
지난 4월 사건 현장을 방문했을 때 ,
there was a bus stop there too.
거기에도 버스 정류장이 있었어요.
What about the unreported case?
신고되지 않은 사건은 어떻게 되나요?
All three cases happened in a desolate area.
세 사건 모두 황량한 지역에서 일어났다.
He's looking at the location.
그 사람이 위치를 보고 있어요.
You figured that out already?
벌써 알아냈나요?
No witnesses, right?
증인은 없지, 그렇지?
That's right.
좋아요.
So if we take Chief Kook's guess and assume that all three
그래서 국과장님의 추측을 받아들여 세 가지 모두
were abducted from a bus stop…
버스 정류장에서 납치됐나요???
That means they were waiting for the bus.
그것은 그들이 버스를 기다리고 있었다는 것을 의미합니다.
What time did this happen?
언제 이런 일이 일어났나요?
All of their phones went radio silent around 1 a.m. in the morning.
새벽 1시쯤 이들의 휴대전화는 모두 무음으로 설정됐다 .
They were waiting for the last bus.
그들은 마지막 버스를 기다리고 있었습니다.
He might have forced them into the car.
그는 그들을 차에 강제로 태웠을 수도 있습니다.
Don't you need at least two people to force an adult into your car?
어른을 차에 태우려면 적어도 두 사람이 필요하지 않나요 ?
They were offered a free ride.
그들은 무료 승차를 제안 받았습니다.
-What? -A free ride, you say.
-무엇? - 무임승차라고 하던데요.
If there are two culprits, there's no good reason
범인이 2명이라면 이유가 없다.
to abduct women at a bus stop.
버스 정류장에서 여성을 납치합니다.
They can just target a woman walking alone and abduct her by force.
그들은 혼자 걷고 있는 여성을 표적으로 삼아 강제로 납치할 수도 있다.
I think there's a high chance that it's the same culprit.
같은 범인일 가능성이 높다고 봅니다 .
-Chief Park. -Yes?
-박과장님. -예?
Let's form an investigation team.
조사팀을 구성하자.
GYEONGGI INVESTIGATION HEADQUARTERS OF SERIAL MISSING WOMEN CASE
경기연쇄실종여성 사건수사본부
JANUARY 2007
2007년 1월
Let us in on the investigation too.
우리도 조사에 참여하자.
We have experience working with the Analysis Team.
우리는 분석팀과 협력한 경험이 있습니다 .
I'm sure we'll come in handy.
우리가 도움이 될 것이라고 확신합니다.
All right, fine.
알았어, 알았어.
I'll ask the Gyeonggi Agency for permission to cooperate.
경기청에 협조를 요청하겠습니다.
-Thank you, sir. -All right.
-감사합니다. -괜찮은.
You'll be working at the Gyeonggi Agency for a while, right?
당분간 경기청 에서 일하시겠죠 ?
Yes, probably.
네 아마도.
Hold on.
기다리다.
Hey, what should I do with this?
야, 이걸 어떻게 해야 하지?
Should I rip it up?
뜯어야 하나?
RESIGNATION LETTER
사직서
-Come on. -Should I?
-어서 해봐요. -내가해야합니까?
You're so twisted.
당신은 너무 뒤틀려 있어요.
Woo-ju. Rip that up into pieces once we leave.
우주. 우리가 떠나면 그것을 조각으로 찢어주세요 .
I'll do as you command.
명령대로 하겠습니다.
-I'm counting on you, Woo-ju. -Sure thing.
-우주님을 믿고 있어요. -확실한 것.
"Woo-ju," please?
"우주" 주세요?
GYEONGGI PROVINCIAL POLICE AGENCY
경기지방경찰청
-Let's get started then. -Yes, sir.
- 그럼 시작해 보겠습니다. -알겠습니다.
MISSING WOMEN CASES IN GYEONGGI
경기도 여성 실종 사건
There were no security cameras at the scene.
현장에는 보안 카메라가 없었습니다 .
Most of those areas don't have any.
그런 지역은 대부분 없어요.
They're building new apartment complexes there.
그들은 거기에 새로운 아파트 단지를 짓고 있습니다.
The district office didn't even look for installation spots.
구청에서는 설치 장소도 찾지 않았다.
The culprit knows the area is pretty desolate
범인은 그 지역이 꽤 황량하다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
with no security cameras.
보안 카메라도 없이.
I think we should install security cameras not just in this area,
내 생각엔 이 지역뿐만 아니라 보안 카메라를 설치해야 할 것 같아요 .
but also at every bus stop with no security cameras in Gyeonggi.
경기도에는 감시 카메라가 없는 모든 버스 정류장에도 마찬가지다 .
-Every single one? -Yes, switch out the old ones too.
- 하나하나? - 네, 오래된 것들도 바꿔보세요.
You can barely make out license plates with the older models.
구형 모델에서는 번호판을 거의 알아볼 수 없습니다 .
You think it's that simple?
그렇게 간단하다고 생각하시나요?
The Ministry of Finance has to…
재무부가해야합니까 ???
Fine. I'll talk to them.
괜찮은. 내가 그들과 얘기해 볼게요.
Then I'll check for areas with no security cameras.
그럼 보안 카메라가 없는 구역을 확인해 보겠습니다 .
-All right. -Thanks, I appreciate it.
-괜찮은. - 고마워요, 고마워요.
A SAFE COUNTRY WITH HAPPY CITIZENS A COUNTRY OF SECURITY POWER
행복한 시민이 있는 안전한 나라, 안보력의 나라
Have you been well?
잘 지내셨나요?
Yes, thanks to you.
네, 고마워요.
Thanks to me?
나 덕분에?
You played a part in my joining the Analysis Team.
제가 분석팀에 합류하는 데 당신이 한 몫을 했습니다 .
I see you can make jokes now.
이제 농담도 할 수 있을 것 같군요.
The rumors about Chief Kook whipping you into shape was true.
국과장님이 당신을 몸매로 만들어준다는 소문은 사실이었습니다.
Yes, he sure did.
예, 그는 확실히 그랬습니다.
I was appointed to a new station so suddenly,
나는 갑자기 새로운 역에 부임하게 되었고 ,
so I couldn't reach out.
그래서 연락을 못했어요.
Anyone would've done the same thing.
누구라도 같은 일을 했을 것이다.
It's all in the past now.
이제 다 과거입니다.
I'm just glad we met again.
우리가 다시 만나서 정말 기뻐요.
Let's do our best.
최선을 다하자.
Did you hear the rumors about you whipping me into shape?
당신 이 나를 몸매로 만든다는 소문을 들었나요 ?
What kind of absolute nonsense is that?
그게 무슨 절대 말도 안되는 소리입니까?
Who whipped who into what?
누가 누구를 무엇에 빠뜨렸나요?
People just love to gossip.
사람들은 단지 험담을 좋아합니다.
What's wrong with it?
무슨 문제가 있나요?
Don't let rumors bother you.
소문이 당신을 괴롭히게 하지 마십시오.
It's true though.
그래도 사실이에요.
The buses run in 40 to 50-minute intervals.
버스는 40~50분 간격으로 운행됩니다.
That's quite a wait.
꽤 기다리네요.
Right. There aren't many taxis either.
오른쪽. 택시도 많지 않습니다.
Even more so at night.
밤에는 더욱 그렇습니다.
He probably had that in mind.
그 사람도 아마 그 점을 염두에 두고 있었을 겁니다.
The security camera installation is finalized, right?
방범카메라 설치가 마무리 되었죠?
Yes. They'll install more in the areas of disappearance
예. 사라진 지역에 더 많이 설치할 거예요
and all nearby locations.
그리고 근처의 모든 위치.
SINBON 2-DONG OFFICE
신본2동 사무실
I hope the cameras help.
카메라가 도움이 되길 바랍니다.
I'm sure he'll be more cautious with the lack of blind spots.
사각지대가 없어 더욱 조심스러울 거라 확신합니다 .
It's been over nine months now.
이제 9개월이 넘었습니다.
I hope they are alive.
나는 그들이 살아 있기를 바랍니다.
At least none of the missing women were found dead.
실종된 여성 중 적어도 한 명도 죽은 채 발견되지 않았습니다.
Yes, you're right.
네 말이 맞아.
We should be hopeful.
우리는 희망을 가져야 합니다.
Let's go over there.
저쪽으로 가자.
He's the statistical analyst of the Analysis Team.
분석팀의 통계분석가입니다 .
His name is Jung Woo-ju. He's a smart guy.
이름은 정우주. 그는 똑똑한 사람입니다.
My name is Yoon Tae-gu.
제 이름은 윤태구입니다.
I'll leave.
난 떠날거야.
Did you have customers who offered to give people a ride?
사람들에게 태워주겠다고 제안한 고객이 있었나요 ?
BUS STOP
버스 정류장
It's cold. Hop in.
추워. 올라 타다.
-I'll take you to the main street. -Right.
- 메인 스트리트까지 데려다줄게. -오른쪽.
SUSPECT ANALYSIS
의심스러운 분석
PROFILING REPORT
프로파일링 보고서
GYEONGGI INVESTIGATION HEADQUARTERS OF SERIAL MISSING WOMEN CASE
경기연쇄 실종여성사건수사 본부
All three cases broke out when the wind chill factor was low.
세 가지 사례 모두 체감온도가 낮을 ​​때 발생했습니다 .
It was a secluded area, so buses didn't come often.
한적한 지역이라 버스가 자주 오지 않더군요.
I stood alone at the bus stop,
버스 정류장에 혼자 서 있었는데,
but a truck came by and offered me a ride out into the main street.
그런데 트럭이 와서 나에게 메인 스트리트까지 태워다 주겠다고 제안했습니다.
You won't find a bus here even if you waited.
여기서는 기다려도 버스를 찾을 수 없습니다 .
The culprit takes advantage of the victim's situation and psychology.
범인은 피해자의 상황과 심리를 이용한다 .
The buses don't run often,
버스가 자주 운행되지는 않지만,
so it's common for people to give rides
그래서 사람들이 차를 태워주는 것이 흔한 일이에요
in that neighborhood.
그 동네에서.
On a cold day, it must've been easier.
추운 날에는 더 쉬웠을 텐데요.
So the culprit used the kind face as a mask to lure them?
그럼 범인은 그 친절한 얼굴을 가면으로 삼아 그들을 유인했다는 걸까요?
Yes.
예.
Even so, how can they gladly hop into a stranger's car?
그럼에도 불구하고 어떻게 낯선 사람의 차에 기꺼이 탈 수 있겠습니까?
They didn't hop in gladly.
그들은 기꺼이 뛰어들지 않았습니다.
The culprit must've convinced them to hop in.
범인은 그들이 뛰어들도록 설득한 게 틀림없어요.
Then the culprit must drive a luxurious sedan that seems familiar.
그렇다면 범인은 낯익은 고급 세단을 운전해야 한다.
Or have something in his car that drives away people's suspicion.
아니면 그의 차에 사람들의 의심을 불러일으키는 무언가가 있을 수도 있습니다.
A family photo? Or stuffed animals?
가족 사진? 아니면 동물 인형?
-A baby? -Let's say a baby is in the car.
-아기? - 차 안에 아기가 있다고 가정해 봅시다.
Then people rarely ask anybody else to join them.
그러면 사람들은 다른 사람에게 가입을 요청하는 경우가 거의 없습니다.
The first thing the victim looks at is the driver.
피해자가 가장 먼저 보는 것은 운전자입니다.
So I think the suspect may look amicable,
그러니까 피의자가 우호적으로 보일 수도 있을 것 같은데,
someone who doesn't draw people's suspicion.
사람들의 의심을 받지 않는 사람 .
I'm sure the culprit isn't intimidating.
범인이 무서운 사람이 아닌 건 확실해요.
Must be likable.
호감이 있어야합니다.
You're right.
네가 옳아.
Hello? Chief Kook.
안녕하세요? 국 실장님.
I'll send you a fax. Please take a look at it.
팩스를 보내드리겠습니다. 한번 살펴보시기 바랍니다.
Yes, a cold case for a missing person.
네, 실종자에 대한 미해결 사건입니다.
Yes, in Gunpo.
네, 군포에요.
GUNPO
군포
Yes, I'll check.
네, 확인해 보겠습니다.
One second.
일초.
Woo-ju just sent over a missing person case.
방금 우주가 실종자 사건을 보냈다 .
The victim is Heo Geum-young, 51 years old, who went missing in Gunpo.
피해자는 군포에서 실종된 허금영( 51)씨다.
And is it similar?
그리고 비슷합니까?
She went missing
그녀는 실종됐다
at a bus stop in a secluded area.
한적한 지역의 버스 정류장에서.
Her phone battery got separated around that area.
그녀의 전화기 배터리는 그 부근에서 분리되었습니다 .
Seems possible.
가능할 것 같습니다.
-He sent us a fax. -I'll pick it up.
-그가 우리에게 팩스를 보냈어요. - 제가 가져갈게요.
No, I got it.
아니요, 알겠습니다.
I'm going to the restroom.
나는 화장실에 갈거야.
-She was 51 years old? -Yes.
-51세였나요? -예.
Hey.
여기요.
We just heard about the cold case in Gunpo--
방금 군포에서 발생한 미제 사건에 대해 들었습니다.
Yes. One second.
예. 일초.
Hey, don't hang up.
이봐요, 끊지 마세요.
It's a word on a missing case.
실종사건에 대한 말씀입니다.
No, not the Gunpo cold case. Not that one. Something else.
아니요, 군포 콜드 케이스는 아닙니다. 그거 말고. 다른 것.
Suwon Seobu Police Station.
수원서부경찰서.
An office worker, in her thirties.
회사원, 30대.
That neighborhood recently became filled with industrial parks.
그 동네는 최근 산업 단지로 가득 차게 되었습니다.
The missing person worked in Haeyong Industrial Park.
실종자는 해용산업단지에서 일했습니다.
She usually commuted by bus at the bus stop
그녀는 보통 버스 정류장에서 버스로 통근했습니다
in front of her workplace.
직장 앞
That area only has industrial parks around,
그 지역 주변에는 산업 단지만 있습니다.
so everything is pitch dark at night.
그래서 밤에는 모든 것이 칠흑같이 어둡습니다.
Her phone battery was pulled out at 7 a.m. the next morning.
다음 날 아침 7시에 휴대폰 배터리가 꺼졌습니다 .
MISSING PERSON
실종자
A HILL IN ANSAN, GYEONGGI PROVINCE
경기도 안산의 어느 언덕
Hello, Chief Park?
안녕하세요, 박과장님?
We found Yoon Jin-sil's body.
윤진실의 시신을 찾았습니다.
The karaoke bar employee who went missing in January.
지난 1월 실종된 노래방 직원 .
Did you see the news?
뉴스 봤어?
She went missing, then was found buried in secret.
그녀는 실종됐다가 비밀리에 묻힌 채 발견됐다.
I should check on my wife.
아내에게 확인해 봐야 할 것 같아요.
That's horrendous.
정말 끔찍해요.
MISSING KARAOKE BAR EMPLOYEE IN HER THIRTIES, FOUND DEAD IN ANSAN
30대 노래방 직원 실종 , 안산서 숨진 채 발견
Get up here!
여기서 일어나세요!
Go up!
위로 가다!
Something might come out, so keep digging up there!
뭔가 나올 수도 있으니 계속 파헤쳐보세요!
Yes!
예!
FOUND NAKED WITH STOCKINGS TIED AROUND THE NECK
목에 스타킹을 묶은 채 나체로 발견됨
GYEONGGI PROVINCIAL POLICE AGENCY
경기지방경찰청
Ansan is pretty far from the last phone signal
안산은 마지막 전화신호가 꽤 멀다.
and where she went missing.
그리고 그녀가 실종된 곳.
You're right.
네가 옳아.
Why didn't he go near Anyang?
왜 안양 근처에는 가지 않았나요?
I'm not sure why he went all the way to Ansan to bury her.
왜 그가 그녀를 묻기 위해 안산까지 왔는지 모르겠습니다 .
The farther one travels, the riskier it becomes.
더 멀리 여행할수록 더 위험해집니다.
He probably didn't make a move by day.
그는 아마도 낮에는 움직이지 않았을 것입니다.
He went around at night when it was difficult
밤에 힘들 때 돌아다녔어요
to spot his car on camera.
카메라에 그의 차를 발견하기 위해.
He either lived in Gyeonggi for a long time,
경기도에서 오래 살았거나 ,
or he must know the area well.
아니면 그 지역을 잘 알아야 합니다.
Gimpo, Anyang, Suwon, and Ansan.
김포, 안양, 수원, 안산.
He usually found the most secluded areas.
그는 대개 가장 외딴 지역을 찾았습니다.
Lots of places don't show up on GPS in that area.
해당 지역의 GPS에 표시되지 않는 장소가 많습니다 .
You're right, on top of that, he buried her
맞아요 게다가 그 사람이 그녀를 묻어줬어요
in a hill 80m away from the road.
도로에서 80m 떨어진 언덕에 있습니다.
If it hadn't been for that elderly man
그 노인이 아니었다면
who goes there every day,
매일 거기 가는 사람,
it would've been impossible for an ordinary person to spot.
보통 사람이라면 알아차리기 불가능했을 것이다 .
Then let's find the cars
그럼 차를 찾아보자
that we can distinguish
우리가 구별할 수 있는 건
from the security footage.
보안 영상에서요.
We have no choice
우리에게는 선택의 여지가 없습니다
but to narrow down our suspects to ex-convicts living in Gyeonggi.
다만, 용의자를 경기도에 거주하는 전과자로 한정하기 위함이다 .
There must be a reason why he chose this spot.
그가 이 자리를 선택한 데에는 이유가 있을 것이다 .
Once we find some suspects, we'll also find the reason.
용의자를 찾으면 이유도 찾아낼 겁니다.
Detective Nam. Put together a list of ex-convicts.
남 형사님. 전과자 목록을 작성하세요.
Yes, sir.
알겠습니다.
AN YU-YEON
안유연
You're sound asleep.
당신은 곤히 잠들어 있습니다.
INSERT CARD
카드 삽입
PLEASE ENTER YOUR PIN
PIN을 입력하세요
Please take your cash.
현금을 챙겨가세요.
Your transaction has been completed.
거래가 완료되었습니다.
Thank you for using Hanyoung Bank.
한영은행을 이용해 주셔서 감사합니다.
CCTV FOOTAGE EVIDENCE
CCTV 영상 증거
Was this the person you saw?
이 사람이 당신이 본 사람이었나?
Yes, his hair and outfit were odd, so I remember him.
네, 머리랑 옷이 이상해서 기억나네요.
-He had this bushy bang. -I see.
-그는 덥수룩한 앞머리를 가졌습니다. -알겠어요.
And he was wearing a dress shirt with sweatsuit pants.
그리고 그는 운동복 바지와 함께 드레스 셔츠를 입고 있었습니다 .
-Was this the jacket too? -Yes.
-이것도 재킷이었나? -예.
He looked at me after he withdrew the money,
그는 돈을 인출한 후 나를 바라보며
so I stared back.
그래서 나는 뒤를 돌아보았다.
Did you see where he went?
그 사람이 어디로 갔는지 봤어?
I wouldn't know.
나는 모른다.
I saw him catching a taxi.
나는 그가 택시를 타는 것을 보았다.
A taxi?
택시로?
A female university student in Gunpo has been missing for 18 days,
군포 여대생 실종 18일째,
so the police began an open search.
그래서 경찰은 공개 수색을 시작했습니다.
The police obtained footage of a man in his twenties to thirties
경찰은 20~30대 남성의 영상을 입수했습니다
withdrawing 700,000 won with this woman's debit card at a bank.
은행에서 이 여성의 직불카드로 70만원을 인출했습니다 .
He's now openly wanted as the key suspect.
이제 그는 주요 용의자로 공개 수배 중입니다.
Yes, all right.
응, 알았어.
I checked with the taxi company,
택시회사에 확인해보니
and they haven't found the driver yet.
아직 운전사를 찾지 못했어요.
If he took a taxi, he probably lives near the bank.
택시를 탔다면 아마도 은행 근처에 살 것입니다.
The bank is close to where she went missing.
은행은 그녀가 실종된 곳과 가깝습니다.
It won't be easy, but let's check every security camera
쉽진 않겠지 만 보안 카메라를 하나하나 확인해 보자
on the streets from the missing point to the bank.
실종 지점에서 은행까지의 거리에서 .
We'll check every footage within six kilometers of the bank.
은행에서 6km 이내의 모든 영상을 확인하겠습니다 .
Everything?
모든 것?
There are at least over 300 cameras out there.
적어도 300개가 넘는 카메라가 있습니다.
Yes, we'll check everything.
네, 다 확인해 보겠습니다.
Please cooperate.
협조해 주십시오.
-Okay.
-좋아요.
Right here.
바로 여기에.
What were you doing then?
그때 당신은 무엇을 하고 있었나요?
I was at home.
난 집에 있었어.
Darn it.
젠장.
Let's keep trying.
계속 노력합시다.
Gyeonggi 89.
경기 89.
-Thank you. -You're welcome.
-감사합니다. -천만에요.
Hold on.
기다리다.
Could you rewind the footage just now?
지금 영상을 되감아 주시겠어요?
Yes. That one. Please zoom in.
예. 하나. 확대해 보세요.
-Chief Kook. Come over here. -Yes?
- 국과장님. 여기로와. -예?
STAY TUNED FOR THE EPILOGUE
에필로그를 계속 지켜봐주세요
Gosh.
이런.
I've been working in the force for about 30 years.
저는 약 30년 동안 군대에서 일해왔습니다 .
And in my opinion,
그리고 제 생각에는,
you're the best cop in Korea.
당신은 한국 최고의 경찰이에요.
That was out of the blue.
그것은 예상치 못한 일이었습니다.
I've never seen you second guess yourself.
나는 당신이 스스로 추측하는 것을 본 적이 없습니다.
You only focus on your job. You don't let the job get to you.
당신은 당신의 일에만 집중합니다. 당신은 그 일을 당신에게 맡기지 않습니다.
So for the past 20 years, I have been watching you
그래서 지난 20년 동안 나는 당신을 지켜봐왔습니다.
doing so well without much trouble.
큰 어려움 없이 너무 잘 지내요.
And I realized that people like you were born to be police officers.
그리고 나는 당신 같은 사람들이 경찰관으로 태어났다는 것을 깨달았습니다.
And I was proud to have a competent junior like you.
그리고 너처럼 유능한 후배가 있다는 게 자랑스러웠다 .
But the guy you scouted, Song Ha-young,
그런데 당신이 스카우트한 송하영.
is just like you.
당신과 똑같습니다.
He reminds me of you in every sense.
그는 모든 면에서 당신을 생각나게 합니다.
How does he remind you of me?
그 사람은 어떻게 당신에게 나를 생각나게 합니까?
Ha-young is young, handsome,
하영이는 젊고 잘생겼고
and looks great with a perm.
파마를 하면 정말 멋있을 것 같아요.
You two can't see it.
너희 둘은 그것을 볼 수 없다.
But in other people's eyes,
하지만 다른 사람들의 눈에는
Kook Young-soo and Song Ha-young…
국영수와 송하영???
are the same.
동일합니다.
So that got me worried all of a sudden.
그래서 갑자기 걱정이 됐어요.
Worried about whom?
누구를 걱정하시나요?
Isn't it obvious? It's you.
분명하지 않나요? 바로 당신이에요.
Why? I'm a grown man.
왜? 나는 어른이다.
It's easy to come back after running away once.
한 번 도망친 뒤 다시 돌아오는 것은 쉽습니다 .
But…
하지만???
two people who never thought about running away
도망칠 생각을 해본 적 없는 두 사람
ended up working together.
결국 같이 일하게 됐다.
So I was worried that…
그래서 걱정했는데???
both of you might give up if one of you crumbled down.
둘 중 한 사람이 무너지면 둘 다 포기할 수도 있습니다 .
You do have a point.
당신은 일리가 있습니다.
That's how I feel right now.
지금 내 기분이 그렇다.
Just like you said, I've been wrong for the last 20 years.
당신이 말했듯이, 나는 지난 20년 동안 틀렸어요.
It doesn't feel like I've been focusing on my job.
일에 집중하고 있는 것 같지 않아요 .
Because I was too busy with my job,
일이 너무 바빴기 때문에,
perhaps I failed to take care of those around me.
아마도 나는 주변 사람들을 돌보지 못했을 것입니다.
And I wonder if I've been doing it wrong the whole time.
그리고 내가 내내 잘못하고 있었던 건 아닌지 궁금해요.
Young-soo.
영수.
Cops are human too.
경찰도 인간이다.
Get in. I had fun today.
타세요. 오늘은 즐거웠습니다.
-Let's grab one more drink. -We've had enough.
- 한잔 더 마시자. - 이제 충분해요.
-Sir, please drive him home safely. -Sure.
- 선생님, 집까지 안전하게 데려다주세요. -확신하는.
Apartment Complex Seven in Mok-dong.
목동 세븐 아파트 단지입니다.
-You can go. -One more drink.
-당신은 갈 수 있습니다. - 한잔 더.
-Bye. -Wait.
-안녕. -기다리다.
One more!
하나 더!
Thanks, Gil-pyo!
고마워, 길표!
Woo Ho-sung?
우호성?
You wanted to see me?
나를 보고 싶었나요?
Can we talk at the station?
역에서 얘기 좀 할 수 있나요?
Are you suspecting me? Do you have evidence?
저를 의심하시나요? 증거가 있나요?
We can't let this guy buy time. He'll destroy all the evidence.
이 사람에게 시간을 벌게 놔둘 수는 없습니다. 그는 모든 증거를 파괴할 것이다.
This bastard is unbelievable.
이 놈은 정말 말도 안 되는 놈이야.
What if I'm not the culprit?
내가 범인이 아니면 어떻게 되나요?
I'm sure he was psychologically pressured.
나는 그가 심리적으로 압박을 받았을 것이라고 확신합니다.
-Who's calling? -This is Woo Ho-sung.
-누구세요? - 우호성 입니다.